Kinesiology Department. Subject files. 1919-1978.
UCLA Library Special Collections
Kinesiology Department. Subject files.
1919-1978
University Archives Record Series 336
UCLA Library Special Collections
2 linear ft. (5 boxes)
Record Series 336 contains the subject files of UCLA's Kinesiology Department, generated between 1919 and 1978.
University of California, Los Angeles. Kinesiology Department.
Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. Advance notice required for access. Contact the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk for paging information.
Historical note
The Department of Kinesiology trace its origins to the Department of Physical Education, which was established in 1915 as part of the Los Angeles State Normal School. In 1919 the department became part of the Teachers College of the Southern Branch, with separate departments for men and women. During the 1920s, the department's efforts were devoted to the training of Physical Education teachers and the administration of the Physical Education classes that were required of all undergraduates. In 1932 the Men's and Women's Gymnasiums were completed. In 1938 the M.S. degree in Physical Education was authorized. In 1939 the department became part of the newly established College of Applied Arts. In 1952 separate divisions for men and women were eliminated. In 1960 the College of Applied Arts was dissolved and replaced by the College of Fine Arts. The Physical Education Department was then transferred to the College of Letters and Science, Division of Life Sciences. In 1962 the revised physical education major was approved and focused on Kinesiology (the science of human movement) and one of three allied fields: physiology, psychology, or sociology. In 1973 the department changed its name to Kinesiology. When Donald T. Hardy retired in 1976, he was recognized as the founding father of the Kinesiology department. The department first offered a Ph.D. degree in Kinesiology in 1979. In 1990 the Kinesiology Department changed its name to the Physiological Sciences Department.
Scope and Content
Record Series 336 contains the subject files of UCLA's Kinesiology Department, generated between 1919 and 1978. Files include correspondence and operational materials regarding such topics as curriculum, faculty, staff, graduate students, press, expenses, and events.
This is an inactive record series; no additional University records are expected to be added.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 3466864
- A.A.H.P.E.R. Convention., 1951-1952. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- A.A.H.P.E.R. - correspondence., 1958. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Administrative Handbook., 1953. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Administrator's Club., 1951. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Alumni Association., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- American Academy of Physical Education., 1941-1943; 1948-1950. (Box 1, Folders 6-7)
- American Association of University Professors., 1942-1949. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Arnold, S. - correspondence., 1977. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Athletic schedules and changes., 1940-1941. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Athletics and Scholarship. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Barnard, J. - correspondence., 1976. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Bookbindery - correspondence., 1977. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Brown, C. - correspondence., 1977. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Business Manager - correspondence., 1941-1944. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Capital Improvement, Building Request., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Catering - correspondence., 1976-1977. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Community Laboratory Experience., 1951-1952. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Comprehensive Study Plan., 1952-1959. (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Conference on Professional Preparation in Health, Phys Ed, and Recreation., 1953-1956. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Convocation - Physical Education - correspondence, guest list., 1941. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Convocation - Physical Education - correspondence., 1942-1943. (Box 2, Folders 2-3)
- Correspondence - miscellaneous., 1919-1942. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Cozens, Frederick W. - correspondence - general., 1919-1936; 1940-1943. (Box 2, Folders 5-6)
- Cratty, J. - correspondence., 1976-1977. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Curricular Hearings - Life Sciences - First Request., 1960. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Dedication of the Walter Camp Memorial - Address of E.K. Hall., 1928. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Degrees of Staff., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Departmental Orders to the Staff., 1939-1940. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Doctoral Competencies., 1954. (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Edgerton, R. - correspondence., 1976-1977. (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Egstrom, G. - correspondence., 1976-1977. (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Exams of the State University of Iowa., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Faculty - responsibilities., 1964-1974. (Box 2, Folder 16)
- First Aid Organization., 1942. (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Gardner, G. - correspondence., 1976-1977. (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Catalogue materials., 1953; 1963-1964; 1972. (Box 2, Folders 19-21)
- Gifts to the Physical Education Department. (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Graduate Education Unit - operating codes., 1953. (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Graduate Students - active., 1954. (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Grant information., 1974-1977. (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Gregor, R. - correspondence., 1976-1977. (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Haradon, J. - correspondence., 1975-1977. (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Hollingsworth, Cecil B. - correspondence., 1940-1973. (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Individual Group on Democracy - Group Process., 1951-1952. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Junior College - correspondence., 1950. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Junior College - study., 1956. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Keogh, J. - correspondence., 1977-1978. (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Kirkendall, Donald - correspondence., 1976. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Legal Aspects of Physical Education., 1953. (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Library - suggestions and reference books., 1923-1924. (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Los Angeles High School - schedule of recitations., 1950. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Maclise, Deming - correspondence., 1940-1942. (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Miller, B. - correspondence, biographical sketch., 1976-1977. (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Men's Gym, Room 206 - general file., 1975-1977. (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Cozens, Frederick W. - correspondence - Ernest Carroll Moore., 1920-1927. (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Morehouse, L. - correspondence., 1975-1977. (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Motions Passed - Kinesiology Department., 1976-1977. (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Mowry, Edith - correspondence., 1974-1977. (Box 3, Folder 15)
- National Physical Education Service - correspondence., 1919-1920. (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Observation information., 1951-1955. (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Observation - public schools., 1974. (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Orientation to Physical Education - evaluations., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Olympic Boxers - correspondence., 1931-1932. (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Personal advising., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Personnel Status - Master Chart A., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Phi Epsilon Kappa., 1946-1950. (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Library - Physical Education., 1951-1952. (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Physical Education - organization chart., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Presentation to the Faculty Women's Club., 1953. (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Press clippings - Intramural Sports., 1939-1940. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Press clippings - Physical Education Department., 1939-1940. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Professor Preparation and Experience Data., 1953-1954. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Provost - correspondence., 1951. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Questionnaires on Distribution of Faculty Member Time., 1953-1954. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Rankin, Lucinda - correspondence., 1976-1977. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Recreation School., 1936-1937; 1939. (Box 4, Folders 7-9)
- Regulations - University., 1938-1945. (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Rehabilitation Agreement., 1958-1959. (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Research in Physical Education., 1925. (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Research Lab., 1938-1939. (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Cost Analysis - Research Studies on., 1954. (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Reynolds, Ruth - Memorial Fund., 1955-1959. (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Royalties - "Group Process.", 1952-1953. (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Rules for Decathlon Events., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Saint Gregory's Playday., 1953. (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Sanbon, Jeanette - correspondence., 1957-1968. (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Scanlan, T.K. - correspondence., 1976. (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Scanlan, T.K. - correspondence., 1977. (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Sellwood Memorial Fund., 1956-1962. (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Smith, J. - correspondence., 1976-1977. (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Snyder, R. - correspondence., 1976-1977. (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Social Welfare Fund., 1974-1976. (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Spaulding, William - correspondence., 1927. (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Sproul, President - correspondence., 1940-1945. (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Stainsby and Taylor - correspondence., 1977. (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Summary of Areas of Professional Preparation., n.d. (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Summer Session - correspondence., 1919. (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Teacher Placement., 1962-1972. (Box 5, Folders 11-12)
- Telephone bills., 1976. (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Telephone information., 1975-1977. (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Travel information., 1974-1977. (Box 5, Folder 15)
- United Way Crusade., 1974-1977. (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Zernicke, Ronald - correspondence., 1975-1977. (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Hunt, Valerie - correspondence - general., 1976-1977. (Box 5, Folder 18)